Guide to the James Alexander Robertson Papers, 1436?-1939
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Alexander Robertson papers 1436?-1939
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Robertson, James Alexander, 1873-1939.
10.0 Linear Feet 1840 Items
Librarian, archivist for State of Maryland, and historian, of Annapolis (Anne Arundel Co.), Md.
Correspondence, notes, and works in manuscript and typescript concerning Philippine history, administrative problems and policies during the early years of American occupation, the Aglipay or Independent Filipino Church, Roman Catholicism, customs, geography, book manufacturing, education, José Rizal, Freemasonry, Filipino senators, and Katipunan of Filipino Secret Society. Many letters center around James Alfred Le Roy, authority on the Philippine Islands.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Alexander Robertson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1940.
Biographical Note
Librarian, archivist for State of Maryland, and historian, of Annapolis (Anne Arundel Co.), Md.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, notes, and works in manuscript and typescript concerning Philippine history, administrative problems and policies during the early years of American occupation, the Aglipay or Independent Filipino Church, Roman Catholicism, customs, geography, book manufacturing, education, José Rizal, Freemasonry, Filipino senators, and Katipunan of Filipino Secret Society. Many letters center around James Alfred Le Roy, authority on the Philippine Islands.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Robertson, James Alexander, 1873-1939
LeRoy, James A--(James Alfred)--1875-1909
Rizal, José--1861-1896
Education -- Philippines
Freemasonry -- Philippines
Historians -- United States -- Correspondence
Secret societies -- Philippines
Philippines -- Church history
Philippines -- History -- Philippine American War, 1899-1902
Philippines -- Social life and customs
Contents of Collection
- James Alexander Robertson Papers, 1436-1939, (24 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
  - James A. LeRoy’s critique of John R. M. Taylor’s The Philippine Insurrection Against the United States (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (photographs), 1436?-1708
  - Letters, 1568-1847
  - Letters, 1850-1897 Jan.
  - Letters, 1897 Feb.-1897 July
  - Letters, 1898-1899
  - Letters, 1900-1901
  - Letters, 1902-1904 (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1905
  - Letters, 1906 Jan-Oct
  - Letters, 1906 Nov-Dec
  - Letters, 1907 Jan-Dec (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1908-1909
  - Letters, 1911-1915
  - Letters, 1920-1939
  - Narrative of the 6th Infantry in the Occupation of the Philippines; Fragment, 1900 (Box 4)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1900
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1903-1906
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1907
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1911 (Box 5)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1912-1913
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1914-1915
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1916-1917
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1918-1919 (Box 6)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1920-1928
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, 1930-1931
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 7)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 8)
  - Creteron?-Vocabulary in Italian, Malese, Suluano, Tagalese, undated
  - Mancayan Township, Philippine Islands. History and Description, undated
  - Mindoro Island, Philippine Islands: Writing of the Mangans
  - Robertson, James A. Books and the Teacher
  - Robertson, James A. The Early History of the Philippines
  - Robertson, James A. The Moro Raids
  - Robertson, James A. Spanish Government in the Philippines
  - Robertson, James A. An 'Uncle Remus' Tale from the Philippines
  - Robertson, James A. Notes on the Philippines
  - Robertson, James A. Notes on the Philippines
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 9)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 10)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 11)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 12)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 13)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 14)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 15)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated (Box 16)
  - Translation of Philippine insurgent documents (Box 17)
  - Articles and notes on the Philippines and other Pacific islands, undated
  - Printed material (photographs), 1565-1898 (Box 18)
  - Printed material on the Philippines, 1896-1912
  - Printed Material on the Philippines, 1913-1917
  - Copy of a Translation of Mabini’s Manifesto regarding the American Occupation and the Philippine Insurrection (Box 19)
  - Printed Material on the Philippines, undated
  - Maps and Diagrams (largely photographs), 1524-1903
  - Philippine Library papers, 1909-1911 (Box 20)
  - Philippine Library papers, 1912-1913
  - Philippine Islands: Photostats of native scripts, including Povedeno Manuscript of 1572 (Box 21)
  - Index to Rizal’s private library
  - Historical sketch of the Philippine library
  - Philippine Library papers, 1932-1936 and undated
  - Philippine Library Association: Minutes and Proceedings
  - Samiel, Isidoro. Modernizing the Libraries in the Philippine Islands
  - The Philippine Library papers, 1914-1915
  - Newspapers clippings (Box 22)
  - Newspapers clippings (Box 23)
  - Four sets of catalog cards
  - Photographs of various churches and miscellaneous photographs (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Oversize-box 19)